<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: javascript | Michele Degges]]></title>
  <link href="http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-09T21:42:47-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michele Degges]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Technical Challenge: Learn from my Mistakes]]></title>
    <link href="http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/blog/2016/03/09/technical-challenge-learn-from-my-mistakes/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-09T20:38:32-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/blog/2016/03/09/technical-challenge-learn-from-my-mistakes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/CMt4ZDx.png?1" alt="Connect4" /></p>

<p>After applying to a few startups on Angellist, I was super excited to have gotten through my very first phone interview. At the end of the call, the HR rep scheduled me for a technical challenge. He said I would have up to 24 hours to complete the challenge, but that I&rsquo;d have to check in at the 2 hour mark and report my progress. I would be assessed on both the first draft of my code at the 2 hour mark, and the final version.</p>

<p>The task was pretty straightforward: to create Connect 4 in the language I felt most comfortable in. Since I applied for a backend position, I wasn&rsquo;t supposed to create any front-end or accept any user input. The program was supposed to simulate the turns taken by players and have a function to print out the board in ASCII, like so:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript ASCII output after two turns have been taken">* * * * * * *
* * * * * * *
* * * * * * *
* * * * * * *
* X O * * * *
</code></pre>

<p>Now.. this was a pretty challenging task for me. I got the basic version down, but it took me about 4 hours to complete and another hour of debugging before I felt comfortable enough to submit the final version. Here&rsquo;s what I learned from the whole process:</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t freak out!</h2>

<p>Once I got the challenge emailed to me, I set an alarm for 2 hours. While this helped me keep track of my time, it also made me really anxious as I saw the minutes slipping by. I would have gotten further along much faster if I didn&rsquo;t obsessively check the time every five minutes.</p>

<h2>Find a quiet place to work</h2>

<p>When living in a house with 20 other people, it&rsquo;s hard to find a quiet place to think, let alone code. My advice is: either lock yourself in your room and ask your roommates not to bother you, or get out of the house for a few hours. I ended up on a park bench for my last- and most productive- hour.</p>

<h2>Hit MVP before trying to get fancy</h2>

<p>Everyone always says to hit MVP first before trying anything fancy, even if your MVP is the most obnoxious piece of code you&rsquo;ve ever written. Now I know why I keep hearing this- it&rsquo;s the best piece of advice out there. Get <strong>something</strong> working and then revise if you have any time left. If not.. you won&rsquo;t have anything working to show for all of your hard work. To reiterate: <strong>GET SOMETHING WORKING!</strong></p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t take my own advice on this one, and I ended up wasting a lot of time trying to debug a function that just wasn&rsquo;t working. At my two hour check-in, I barely had any working code to show.</p>

<h2>If you don&rsquo;t have time..</h2>

<p>Sometimes there just isn&rsquo;t enough time to refactor. I submitted the final version of this challenge about 5:30 hours in. It isn&rsquo;t fancy- actually, it barely hits MVP- but it works.</p>

<p>I had a lot going on- I had another in-person interview to prepare for, I had to continue working on another piece of code that my team needed to present the next day, and I was just plain exhausted from coding so much.</p>

<h2>Are you sure you want to submit?</h2>

<p>The thing is- I probably could have created a more elegant solution if I had spent more time on it. That&rsquo;s the thing about coding: it&rsquo;s impossible not to improve. The more time you spend coding, the better you get, the smarter you become.</p>

<p>I did have the full 24 hours to finish the challenge, but I submitted at around the 6 hour mark. In hindsight, I should have slept on it for a few hours and woken up to work on it the next day with a fresh pair of eyes. I was afraid that taking all of the allotted time would reflect negatively on my abilities, but you know what- I think it&rsquo;s better to take more time to submit something you can be proud of than to submit the bare minimum and regret it all week.</p>

<h2>My solution</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m not very proud of my code, nor am I happy with how far I got on this challenge, because I really did just barely get MVP. I don&rsquo;t expect this to land me the job I was going for. In fact, I will be suuuper surprised if I get any reply back from that HR guy, but that&rsquo;s part of the reason I&rsquo;m posting this now.</p>

<h2>This is honestly the skill level I&rsquo;m at right now</h2>

<p>This is how I code. This is truly a reflection of where I&rsquo;m at. Sometimes it takes me forever to get anywhere (like it did with this challenge). Sometimes it takes me minutes. That&rsquo;s how it is for us stone-cold beginners. But you know what&hellip; that&rsquo;s okay! I&rsquo;m getting there, and you&rsquo;ll get there too. With each new challenge we take on and refuse to give up on, we get better and better. We shave minutes off of our time. We&rsquo;re able to think more logically and efficiently. And most of all, we can feel proud of ourselves because we really did try our hardest.. and we didn&rsquo;t give up!</p>

<p>So without further ado, here&rsquo;s my super basic (somewhat randomized) version of Connect 4.</p>

<pre><code class="javascript Basic Connect 4">/* A randomized Connect 4 Javascript Game that works with any board size */

'use strict';

var gameBoard = [];
var player1;
var player2;
var gameOver = 0;

const boardSize = 4;

function gameInit() {
  for (var i=0; i&lt;boardSize; i++) {
    gameBoard[i] = [];
    for (var j=0; j&lt;boardSize; j++) {
      gameBoard[i][j] = '*';
    }
  }
  console.log('Start Game');
  console.log(gameBoard);
  player1 = 1;
  player2 = 0;
}

function randomMove() {
  return Math.floor(Math.random() * (boardSize));
}

function piecePlacement(x, y, piece) {
  var placed = 0;

  while (!placed) {
    if (gameBoard[x][y] === '*') {
      gameBoard[x][y] = piece;
      placed = 1;
      return;
    }
    else {
      //iterate up through column
      for (var i=x-1; i&gt;=0; i--) {
        if (gameBoard[i][y] === '*') {
          gameBoard[i][y] = piece;
          placed = 1;
          return;
        }
      }
    }
    var x = boardSize-1;
    var y = randomMove();
  }
}

function move(player) {
  var x = boardSize-1;
  var y = randomMove();
  var piece;

  if (player === 1) {
    console.log('Player 1 (Os) turn');
    piece = 'O';
  }
  else {
    console.log('Player 2 (Xs) turn');
    piece = 'X';
  }

  checkWin(player);
  piecePlacement(x, y, piece);
  console.log(gameBoard);
}

function winning(count) {
  if (count === boardSize) {
    return 1;
  }
  return 0;
}

function checkVertical(piece) {
  var count = 0;
  var j=0;

  while (j&lt;boardSize) {
    for (var i=0; i&lt;boardSize; i++) {
      if (gameBoard[i][j] === piece) {
        count += 1;
      }
    }
    if (winning(count)) {
      return 1;
    }
    j += 1;
    count = 0;
  }
}

function checkHorizontal(piece) {
  var i=0;
  var count=0;

  while (i&lt;boardSize) {
    for (var j=0; j&lt;boardSize; j++) {
      if (gameBoard[i][j] === piece) {
        count += 1;
      }
    }
    if (winning(count)) {
      return 1;
    }
    i += 1;
    count = 0;
  }
}

function checkDiagonals(piece) {
  var count = 0;

  for (var i=0; i&lt;boardSize; i++) {
    for (var j=0; j&lt;boardSize; j++) {
      if (i === j) {
        if (gameBoard[i][j] === piece) {
          count += 1;
        }
      }
    }
  }
  if (winning(count)) {
    return 1;
  }

  count = 0;
  i=0;
  j=boardSize-1;

  while (i&lt;boardSize) {
    while (j&gt;=0) {
      if (gameBoard[i][j] === piece) {
        count += 1;
      }
      j -= 1;
      i += 1;
    }
  }

  if (winning(count)) {
    return 1;
  }
}

function checkStalemate(piece) {
  var count = 0;

  for (var i=0; i&lt;boardSize; i++) {
    for (var j=0; j&lt;boardSize; j++) {
      if (gameBoard[i][j] != '*') {
        count +=1 ;
      }
    }
  }

  if (count &gt;= boardSize*boardSize) {
    return 1;
  }
}

function checkWin(player) {
  var piece;

  if (player === 1) {
    piece = 'O';
  }
  else {
    piece = 'X';
    player = 2;
  }

  if ((checkVertical(piece)) || (checkHorizontal(piece)) || checkDiagonals(piece)) {
    console.log('Game over');
    console.log('Player '+ player + ' won!');
    gameOver = 1;
    return;
  }
  if (checkStalemate(piece)) {
    console.log('Game over');
    console.log('Stalemate!');
  }
}

function play() {
  gameInit();
  while (!gameOver) {
    move(player1);
    if (gameOver) {
      return;
    }
    move(player2);
  }
}

play();
</code></pre>

<p>Feel free to reach out to me via email (<a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x6d;&#x64;&#x65;&#103;&#103;&#105;&#101;&#115;&#64;&#103;&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;">&#109;&#100;&#101;&#x67;&#103;&#105;&#x65;&#115;&#64;&#103;&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;</a>), or on Twitter (@mdeggies) :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
