<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: octopress | Michele Degges]]></title>
  <link href="http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-02T01:25:12-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michele Degges]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating Jekyll with gh-pages]]></title>
    <link href="http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/blog/2016/03/02/integrating-jekyll-with-gh-pages/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-02T00:29:36-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://mdeggies.github.io/blog/blog/2016/03/02/integrating-jekyll-with-gh-pages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Integrating Jekyll with gh-pages shouldn&rsquo;t take more than 15 minutes. The idea is simple: you already have a personal website hosted on yourusername.github.io. The goal is to create a blog and host it on yourusername.github.io/blog. Sounds easy, right?!</p>

<p>Well, not so fast.. Jekyll and gh-pages are not the stellar, easy-going couple that they claim to be. Integrating the two- especially when you already have a static site at yourusername.github.io- is not such an easy task.</p>

<p>In comes Octopress! Octopress is a static blogging framework built on top of Jekyll. It&rsquo;s supposed to allow for easy integration and deployment. I was so excited when I found out it existed.. but then I started reading through it&rsquo;s documentation and my excitement fizzled out pretty quick.</p>

<h1>The goal</h1>

<p>We know the goal- to get a blog up and running on gh-pages- specifically, gh project pages- since we already have a site at yourusername.github.io</p>

<h1>The steps</h1>

<p>First, create a new repo on github.com called blog. This is where our octopress site will live. Copy the location (<a href="https://github.com/yourusername/blog.git">https://github.com/yourusername/blog.git</a>).</p>

<p>In your terminal, navigate to the directory you want to create and edit your blog project in. In that directory, perform these commands:</p>

<ul>
<li>git clone git://github.com/imathis/octopress.git blog</li>
<li>cd blog</li>
<li>git init</li>
<li>git add .</li>
<li>git remote add origin <a href="https://github.com/yourusername/blog.git">https://github.com/yourusername/blog.git</a></li>
<li>git commit -m &ldquo;initializing octopress&rdquo;</li>
<li>git push origin master</li>
</ul>


<p>You&rsquo;ve just initialized your blog project with Octopress! Now let&rsquo;s set everything up:</p>

<ul>
<li>gem install bundler</li>
<li>bundle install</li>
<li>rake setup_github_pages</li>
</ul>


<p>At this point, you&rsquo;ll be asked to give a repository url. Use the same url you copied from github (<a href="https://github.com/yourusername/blog.git">https://github.com/yourusername/blog.git</a>)</p>

<ul>
<li>git   config branch.master.remote origin</li>
<li>rake install</li>
<li>rake generate</li>
<li>rake deploy</li>
<li>rake preview</li>
</ul>


<p>Rake install will install the default Octopress theme on your site. Generate and deploy will get it running, and preview will allow you to preview your site locally at localhost:4000</p>

<p>To install a new theme, such as ioveracker&rsquo;s MNML, follow these steps:</p>

<ul>
<li>git clone git://github.com/ioveracker/mnml.git .themes/mnml</li>
<li>rake install[&lsquo;mnml&rsquo;]</li>
<li>rake generate</li>
<li>rake deploy</li>
<li>rake preview</li>
</ul>


<h1>And that&rsquo;s how it&rsquo;s done</h1>

<p>As always, don&rsquo;t forget to git add .&amp;&amp; git commit -m &ldquo;updating site..&rdquo; &amp;&amp; git push -u origin master to save your changes on yourusername.github.io/blog!</p>

<p>If you have any questions, feel free to hit me up at mdeggies@gmail.com, or message me on twitter. Have fun exploring Octopress and Jekyll!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
